בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is יג yud gimmel
and we are finally turning from
the last part of the משנה, Mishnah, which the whole first part
of the משנה Mishnah was figuring out the different function of all
of the מוספים musafim of the חטאת chatas of all the מוספים
musafim and how they're all variations of טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash. And
then the last part, which was all a whole derivation of the
fact that שבועות שתים שהן ארבע shevuot shtayim she'hein arba based on
other things which are two which are four, again, but like I
said at the beginning of the משנה, Mishnah, maybe we'll reassess this
when we finish the פרק perek which we'll be doing tomorrow, like
what is the reason to be completely immersing us in this discussion
right before discussing the whole issue of a שבועה. shevuah. But the
end of the משנה Mishnah turns to sort of like a further
digression, but at least it gets to something that's I think a
little bit more relevant or of indirect interest to us, which should
always be interesting to us, but this is at least more direct
more connected to our lives, which is the question not of טומאת
מקדש tumat mikdash and the קרבנות korbanot that affect טומאת מקדש tumat
mikdash because a lot of those started with the קרבן korban of
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, whether it was the goat on the inside,
which did this case which you knew at the beginning and you
didn't know at the end, or the מוסף musaf at the outside,
which is a case where you knew at the end but not
at the beginning. Anyway, now we talk about the goat of יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, which has nothing to do with טומאת מקדש, tumat
mikdash, but which atones for all of the sins. And the משנה
Mishnah says, whether it's weighty or light, whether it's מזיד mezid or
שוגג, shogeg, whether you knew or you didn't know, the גמרא Gemara
says "know or didn't know" means if it was initially done בשוגג
beshogeg and now it's a question of bringing an אשם asham or
not, it's a doubtful sin. Okay, all of those variations, the goat
that's sent over the cliff on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that atones
for. Okay, the one thing it doesn't sort of do is get
you out of an obligation of a חטאת. chatas. If you sin
בשוגג beshogeg and you know you sinned for sure and you became
aware you sinned or whatever, then you still have to bring your
חטאת. chatas. Okay, but now we pick up with this at the
bottom of יב עמוד ב. yud bet amud bet. So it says
the following:
האי עשה היכי דמי, Hai aseh heichi dami, line starts with the
word ידעום או לא, yedaom o lo, four lines from the bottom.
What's the case where it says that the goat atones for the
positive מצוות mitzvot that you did not perform? אי דלא עביד תשובה,
Idalo avid teshuvah, if you didn't do תשובה, teshuvah, "Yeah, I didn't
do it, who cares?" Okay, so זבח רשעים תועבה, zevach reshaim to'evah,
so the sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination. Meaning, it's an
interesting way of phrasing the question. If you didn't do תשובה, teshuvah,
why should we think that the sacrifice atones for you? You know,
we can accept the idea that it atones even for a willful
sin, although normally a sacrifice only atones for an unintentional sin, but
it's one thing that the sin initially was willful, and now you
have remorse. So now at least you're in a state of seeking
forgiveness, right? And there we can understand that maybe even though even
if it was initially willful, maybe the sacrifice will atone. But if
you're not now in a state of remorse and you're not seeking
forgiveness, why should anything wipe the slate clean for you in this
context? But again, the phrase זבח רשעים תועבה zevach reshaim to'evah is
also framing in a slightly different way. It's not just saying the
sacrifice shouldn't atone, it's almost saying that it should be an invalid
sacrifice, right? And this sort of gets into a whole discussion of
the גמרא, Gemara, like, do you accept sacrifices from people that have
completely rejected God and rejected the tradition? You know, do you accept
the sacrifice of a מומר mumar and so on? Is the fact
that you are now at least vis-a-vis this sin, maybe you're deeply
regretful for your other things, but this one sin you say like,
"I don't care that I did it," right, should that at least
vis-a-vis that sin considered like you're a רשע rasha and therefore not
only should it not atone for you, but maybe like, you know,
the sacrifice can't even be considered like, you know, we don't even
want your sacrifice. Right, I understand there's a difference between saying like,
do we want your sacrifice and does the sacrifice atone? Anyway, it's
sort of bundling it up together. What's the purpose of somebody bringing
a sacrifice if they don't believe in השם? Hashem? Right, so okay,
let's say they believe in השם, Hashem, let's say they believe in
God but they've rejected Judaism but they still want to bring a
קרבן korban to the Jewish God, you know, cases like that, would
we accept the sacrifice? Not a question of would it atone, right?
So there's a גמרא Gemara that basically says you don't accept sacrifices
from like a מומר, mumar, from somebody that has like, you know,
actively rejected. But the
context would be you believe in God, he doesn't believe in this
particular... I know, I understand, okay. I don't want to get into
it, I just want to point out the difference between saying does
the sacrifice
atone, like, if you haven't shown remorse do you deserve to be
forgiven for the sin, or the very specific concrete issue like like
this you know like this sacrifice should not even be considered, we
shouldn't even want a sacrifice brought in this context, if this is
still your relationship anyway to the sin. Anyway, one way or another,
the point clearly is is that it shouldn't work if you haven't
done תשובה. teshuvah. אי דעביד תשובה, Id'avid teshuvah, now if you've done
תשובה, teshuvah, כל יומא נמי, kol yoma nami, so you don't need
יום כיפור Yom Kippur and the goat. Any day you do תשובה
teshuvah for a מצות עשה, mitzvat aseh, the idea is is that
if it's
the... Okay? דתניא? de-tanya? No, for non-doing of an עשה, aseh, no.
דתניא ותנא ברייתא, de-tanya ve-tana baraita, עבר על מצות עשה ועשה תשובה,
avar al mitzvat aseh ve-asah teshuvah, if you transgressed a positive מצוה
mitzvah and you did תשובה, teshuvah, לא זז משם עד שמוחלין לו.
lo zaz mi-sham ad she-mochalin lo. You like you don't move from
there until God forgives you, it's almost like that image of חוני
המעגל, Choni HaMa'agal, but I'm not going to move from here until
you sort of bring down the rain, meaning but you sort of
like are entitled to immediate forgiveness once you do תשובה. teshuvah. So
who needs יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? So and who needs the goat?
So אמר רבי זירא, amar Rabbi Zeira, said רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
for this type of an עשה. aseh. בעומד במרדו, be-omed be-meredo, you're
right. If it's a positive מצוה, mitzvah, the only reason you would
need a goat is that you are not doing תשובה. teshuvah. And
here it reframes not doing תשובה teshuvah in a more active and
even aggressive way. It's not just the passive non-performance of תשובה, teshuvah,
but עומד במרדו, omed be-meredo, you're standing in your state of rebellion
like you know that's pretty harsh like, alright I didn't get around
to doing תשובה, teshuvah, whatever. No, the fact that you're choosing to
not do תשובה teshuvah is not the lack of a choice, it's
an active choice to continue to say that you don't care. There's
actually it's interesting רמב"ן Ramban in his דרשה לראש השנה, drasha le-Rosh
Hashanah, you know I don't know how you know the sort of
classic you know idea that the rabbi שבת תשובה Shabbat Shuvah and
שבת הגדול Shabbat HaGadol would give a big דרשה, drasha, so it
depends on like what the who the rabbi is and what the
community is the proportion between how much of that דרשה drasha is
like talmudic pyrotechnics and הלכתי halakhic discussion and how much of it
is like מוסר. mussar. So you know so so I you know
the community I grew up in the rabbi spent like 45 minutes
on some הלכתי halakhic discourse which nobody in the community followed and
then he spent the last like five minutes or whatever on some
מוסר mussar or ten minutes on some מוסר. mussar. Anyway the רמב"ן
Ramban in his דרשה לראש השנה drasha le-Rosh Hashanah spends like he
it's like 50 page work, it's basically a commentary on מסכת ראש
השנה. Masechet Rosh Hashanah. He spends the entirety of it dealing with
like הלכתי halakhic talmudic analysis of all the different aspects of the
הלכות halakhos of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. The last paragraph is מוסר.
mussar. Okay?
And the
last paragraph basically says he says look this תשובה, teshuvah, the opportunity
for תשובה teshuvah that God has given us is a great gift
but it could also be a great liability. It's a great gift
because you could do תשובה teshuvah and then be forgiven. But it's
a great liability because he says if God had never given us
the opportunity to do תשובה, teshuvah, then if you didn't do תשובה
teshuvah you'd only sinned once. But now that God's given us the
opportunity to do תשובה, teshuvah, if you're choosing not to do תשובה,
teshuvah, every single minute you're continuing to sin because you're continuing to
basically make a statement that you're holding on to your past sin,
you're choosing not to let go of it, you're choosing to be
like עומד במרדו, omed be-meredo, standing in your state of rebellion, so
you better all do תשובה. teshuvah. Anyway, that was the רמב"ן. Ramban.
Anyway, so I just thought that's interesting like thinking about it as
but not just the passive non-performance of תשובה. teshuvah. אמר רבי זירא
בעומד במרדו, amar Rabbi Zeira be-omed be-meredo, yeah! You're not doing תשובה,
teshuvah, you're actively continuing to say I am glad, you know implicitly
you're actively continuing to say I have no regrets for having done
this sin, nevertheless יום כיפור Yom Kippur forgives you. Okay? So now
you might say maybe for a positive מצוה. mitzvah. Let's take a
look. דרבי היא, de-Rabbi hi, our משנה Mishnah is going according to
רבי. Rabbi. דתניא ותנא ברייתא, de-tanya ve-tana baraita, רבי אומר: Rabbi omer:
על כל עבירות שבתורה בין עשה תשובה בין לא עשה תשובה יום
הכיפורים מכפר. al kol averos she-ba-Torah bein asah teshuvah bein lo asah
teshuvah Yom HaKippurim mechaper.
All of the sins, not just the מצות עשה. mitzvat aseh. We
were bothered with מצות עשה. mitzvat aseh. All the sins, you could
have been מחלל שבת, mechalel Shabbos, you could have done like the
worst sins possible and nevertheless בין אדם למקום, bein adam la-makom, thank
you,
and even if you didn't do תשובה, teshuvah, the power of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur is God wants you each year to start with
a clean slate. So the idea is just you know just survive
to יום כיפור Yom Kippur and you'll get a free start again.
Okay? So בין עשה תשובה בין לא עשה תשובה יום הכיפורים מכפר,
bein asah teshuvah bein lo asah teshuvah Yom HaKippurim mechaper, יום כיפור
Yom Kippur atoned. חוץ, chutz, there's one exception or three exceptions. מפרק
עול, mi-porek ol, somebody who casts off the yoke, rejects God and
the מצוות, mitzvos, okay, ומגלה פנים בתורה, u-megaleh panim ba-Torah, sort of
you know has a brazen face towards the תורה. Torah. This phrase
מגלה פנים בתורה megaleh panim ba-Torah is often misinterpreted because often
a gloss is added in, שלא כהלכה, she-lo ka-halacha, which sort of
means like you know sort of like because we say שבעים פנים
לתורה, shivim panim la-Torah, so some people often misread it as oh
somebody who explains a גמרא gemara or a
הלכה halacha in a way that's not consistent with the הלכה. halacha.
That's not true. That's not such a terrible I mean whatever it's
a bad thing, but it's not in this rank of these terrible
sins. Okay. This the phrase is not שלא כהלכה, she-lo ka-halacha, just
מגלה פנים. megaleh panim. The word גילוי פנים gillui panim means to
act brazenly. So you act brazenly vis-a-vis the תורה. Torah. What does
that mean? You could say it means like you sin, you know
with in an active of rebellion. You're not just a willful sinner,
you're like a להכעיס le-hachis sinner. You do it as a way
of actively rejecting God or you know not rejecting God whatever like
rejecting the מצוות mitzvos or doing... It could be about sin, but
רש״י Rashi particularly emphasizes the word תורה, Torah, which means that your
relationship to תורה Torah is one, like Michael said it well, of
like scoffing. It's like, you might even do all the מצוות, mitzvot,
but you just say, "Ugh, this is so stupid, this פסוק." pasuk.
You know? "Ugh, why would God have said such a thing?" You
know, not in a theoretical, philosophical way, but like in a dismissive,
scoffing type of a way. So if you look at רש״י, Rashi,
רש״י Rashi says: מגלה פנים בתורה, megaleh panim ba'Torah, three lines down
from the top: בא על דברי תורה בחוצפה ובגילוי עזות פנים, ba
al divrei Torah be'chutzpah u'vegilluy azut panim, כגון מנשה שהיה יושב ודורש
באגדות של דופי. kegon Menashe she'haya yoshev vedoresh be'agadot shel dofi. לא
היה לו למשה לכתוב אלא ותמנע היתה פילגש, lo haya lo le'Moshe
lichtov ella ve'Timna hayta pilegesh, וילך ראובן בימי קציר חטים. vayeilech Reuven
bimei ketzir chitim. Why'd משה Moshe have to write this story? This
is such a stupid story. What's it doing in the תורה? Torah?
You know? And again, not in a way of asking a question,
"Why is this in the תורה?" Torah? but as a way of
being dismissive and brazen and so on. So
if you look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi reads it, not to
God and מצוות, mitzvot, but it's a relationship to תורה. Torah. Okay?
So חוץ מפר, chutz mipar, I think רמב״ם Rambam in פירש המשניות
Peirush HaMishnayot says it means to sin like as a להכעיס. lehach'is.
That he's talking about an act of sin, but you're doing it
like with brazenness. What? Yeah, exactly. Okay, so חוץ, chutz, so the
three things. So יום כיפור Yom Kippur will atone for any sin,
even willful, as long as it's like a type of a willful
out of, you know, lust or desire or whatever, lack of control
of your appetitive stuff. But if it's rejecting God, פורק עול, porek
ol, מגלה פנים בתורה, megaleh panim ba'Torah, ומפר ברית בשר, umefeir brit
basar, or it's reversing the ברית מילה. brit milah. That's why it
has the word ברית בשר, brit basar, so you should understand we
don't just mean this metaphorically, right? It is annulling the flesh covenant,
the reversing the ברית מילה. brit milah. Wait, but isn't it also
someone who just goes through life not getting a ברית? brit? If
he... No, I don't... interesting, I don't think maybe, that's interesting. I
think this is more active though.
But maybe somebody's making a conscious choice, you know, maybe. Like their
father didn't do it because their father didn't believe in ברית מילה
brit milah and then the son also doesn't believe and he's making
an active choice, maybe. Okay? שאם עשה תשובה, she'im asa teshuvah, those
are the worst. But even those, תשובה teshuvah will work. שאם עשה
תשובה, she'im asa teshuvah, those you need תשובה teshuvah and יום כיפור
Yom Kippur to go with יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. שאם עשה תשובה
יום הכפורים מכפר, she'im asa teshuvah Yom HaKippurim mechapeir, if you do
תשובה, teshuvah, then יום כיפור Yom Kippur will be מכפר, mechapeir, not
תשובה teshuvah alone. ואם לאו אין יום הכפורים מכפר, ve'im lav ein
Yom HaKippurim mechapeir, it does not atone. By the way,
I also want to point out a subtle shift that's occurred, that's
going to continue to occur for today. We have totally forgotten about
the goat that's going over the cliff. It now has become that
יום כיפור Yom Kippur itself is מכפר, mechapeir, which is of course
an important shift once we no longer have the goat, so to
be thinking about the relevance for us. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara has said our משנה mishnah that needs the goat, and now
we're saying that needs יום כיפור Yom Kippur and is basically talk...
and how does that make sense if it's an עשה? aseh? So
it's basically talking about somebody who has not done תשובה. teshuvah. And
then we're talking about somebody who hasn't done תשובה teshuvah for any
of these sins, even the heaviest sins: כרת, karet, מיתת בית דין.
mitat beit din. You know, after basically just going through an entire
long פרק, perek, long מסכת masechet of סנהדרין Sanhedrin and then מכות
Makkot about all the ways you're punished for your willful sin, now
we're finding out the way the גמרא Gemara is reading it, that
if בית דין beit din didn't get their hands on you and
either there weren't witnesses or התראה, hatra'ah, whatever it was, even a
willful sin, comes יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, slate is wiped clean. Okay?
Even, not only if it was a willful sin, even if it
was a willful sin that you didn't do תשובה teshuvah for. You
could have willfully been מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbat, not one bit of
remorse, right? And יום כיפור Yom Kippur will be מכפר. mechapeir. You
get to start from a clean slate, day one. בית דין beit
din could still get you, right, exactly. If there's witnesses or whatever,
יום כיפור Yom Kippur doesn't get you out of the hands of
בית דין. beit din. Okay, but if somehow you've escaped בית דין,
beit din, you know, there weren't
witnesses or there were but they're not reporting or whatever it was,
no matter if it was intentional, no matter if you continue to
be happy that you did it, right? It's pretty amazing what יום
כיפור Yom Kippur is מכפר. mechapeir. Okay, it reads רבי, Rabbi, right,
but now we're saying that's our משנה. mishnah. Okay, with the exception
of these big three. And even these big three, תשובה teshuvah will
also work, plus יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But would we say it's
חוץ מגילוי עריות שפיכות דמים ועבודה זרה? chutz migilluy arayot shefichut damim
ve'avodah zarah? Correct, correct. גילוי עריות שפיכות דמים ועבודה זרה, gilluy arayot
shefichut damim ve'avodah zarah, all of those יום כיפור Yom Kippur will
be מכפר. mechapeir. Okay, at least according to רבי, Rabbi, as long
as you're still in the פרשה, parsha, as long as you're still
in the ברית, berit, as long as you still have a relationship
with God. You haven't rejected תורה, Torah, you haven't rejected God, you
haven't rejected the ברית. berit. Once you're still... once we're still in
relationship, God is sort of saying, then we're just going to, like
an amnesty day. We're going to try to start all over again.
But again, the funny thing is, you don't even need to like,
you know, what is it? Like amnesty day often is you return
your library books, you won't get fined, you return your guns, you
won't get whatever. No, you don't have to do anything! You just
get wiped clean, so you start over again. And you know, what
was it, all of סנהדרין Sanhedrin stuff, you go up to the
עולם הנשמות, olam haneshamot, you're still, you know, like what's... Well, okay,
so Rav Soloveitchik explained, so of course, not getting punished for your
sins is not having spent a virtuous life doing מצוות, mitzvot, number
one. Okay, it might be that you don't get punished. it doesn't
mean that you actually now are like you know have a lot
of מצוות mitzvot to your credit. Number one, or that you've you
know spent your life developing yourself and getting closer to God. So
you still have all of that you know and also רב סולובייצ'יק
Rav Soloveitchik once explained you know the difference between כפרה kappara and
I'm trying to remember what the other phrase טהרה tahara I think
was the phrase he used. And he also said תשובה מאהבה, teshuva
me'ahava, תשובה מיראה. teshuva miyirah. Anyway, and he basically said he wasn't
the only one to say this obviously but he said it in
a very nice way. But he basically distinguished between the types of
things that are like you won't get punished as opposed to תשובה
teshuva which is like transformational which makes you into a different type
of a person. So it's one thing to say you're not going
to get punished, okay? It's another thing to say that you know
by going through a process of תשובה teshuva a genuine process of
תשובה teshuva you transform who you are. You can become— like you
could be a רשע rasha who's not going to get punished. If
you're so happy that you were מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat and have
no remorse, בגברא begavra as we would say in ישיביש Yeshivish language,
you're still a רשע, rasha, but you're just not going to get
punished for your past sins. Like תשובה teshuva which is about personal
transformation transforms you from like a רשע rasha to a צדיק. tzaddik.
So there's— it's right, we don't mean to just say it's all
trivial, okay. Anyway, so that's רבי, Rebbi, and that's what we're saying
our משנה mishna is.
Now, how do you know this?
דתניא, detanya, מאי טעמא דרבי, mai ta'ama deRebbi, what's his reasoning? דתניא
תנו רבנן בברייתא, detanya tanu rabbanan bevraita, כי דבר ה' בזה, ki
devar Hashem baza, because God's word he has denigrated.
זה הפורק עול ומגלה פנים בתורה. ze haporek ol umegale panim baTorah.
So דבר ה' devar Hashem רש"י Rashi says, it meaning the דבר
ה' devar Hashem means like the first word of the עשרת הדברות,
aseret hadibrot, אנכי ה' אלהיך. anochi Hashem elokecha. So to be sort
of you know to denigrate that is to reject God altogether. That's
that's the idea of פורק עול. porek ol. And מגלה פנים בתורה
megale panim baTorah is because דבר ה' devar Hashem could also mean
all the words of God, any of the words of the תורה.
Torah. So to treat it in a derogatory— not derogatory, in a
in a way of in a dismissive, denigrating, brazen way, that's also
דבר ה' בזה, devar Hashem baza, just the words of the תורה,
Torah, okay. זה פורק עול ומגלה פנים. ze porek ol umegale panim.
ואת מצותו הפר, ve'et mitzvato hefar, and his מצוות mitzvot you have
annulled. זה המפיר ברית בשר. ze hamefir brit basar. So that's the
you know that that's the— what is the one מצוה mitzvah that
symbolizes the idea of the covenant or to that that it would
you know that would be symbolic of like annulling a covenant? That
would be the the ברית brit of the flesh, the circumcision.
הכרת תכרת, hikaret tikaret, will surely be cut off. הכרת לפני יום
הכיפורים תכרת לאחר יום הכיפורים. hikaret lifnei Yom HaKippurim tikaret le'achar Yom
HaKippurim. Here's how he learned that יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim is not
מכפר. mechapper. Interesting, right? רבי Rebbi doesn't have to prove that יום
כיפור Yom Kippur is מכפר mechapper for even willful sins that you
didn't do תשובה. teshuva. Like maybe he— that's his starting point, יום
כיפור Yom Kippur is מכפר mechapper for everything even if you haven't
done תשובה. teshuva. I'm just going to say based on this verse,
I see that there are three things it's not מכפר mechapper for.
Three things even after יום כיפור Yom Kippur you're not atoned for.
But does he explain why we need all these שעירים se'irim and
whatever it is? Well, we know, that's our משנה. mishna. What do
you mean? טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tum'at mikdash vekodashav, all those types of
things, meaning why can't you just the שעיר se'ir that goes off
the cliff do it? No, like it would just say יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, I had a יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Well
the גמרא Gemara is completely ignoring the way that it just very
subtly transitioned from the קרבנות korbanot to יום כיפור Yom Kippur itself.
You know, I assume the answer would be when there were the
קרבנות korbanot and the קרבנות korbanot did it, now without the קרבנות
korbanot the day itself does it. But that's a very obviously critical
question and the גמרא Gemara I think very intentionally allowed us to
just slide from one to the other you know. So, all right,
so anyway, does like idolatry fall into one of those categories, like
what does that mean? Oh, well would would would that be פורק
עול? porek ol? Well, there are two forms of idolatry, you know,
I mean or we could speak about three forms of idolatry. There's
a form of idolatry which is worshipping God but worshipping God through
images. So presumably that would not be פורק עול. porek ol. You're
corrupting the worship of God, it's a terrible sin, it's יהרג ואל
יעבור yehareg ve'al ya'avor and all that, but it's not a פורק
עול, porek ol, you're not rejecting God. Then there's an idolatry of
actually believing in other gods, right? But there's a believing in other
gods and a rejection of God. I'm going to go worship the
בעל, ba'al, I don't believe in this Jewish God, okay? That would
be a פורק עול, porek ol, right? The interesting question is what
do you think about somebody who is like a very what they
call the syncretist or something, you know, that basically sure, I'm a
big pluralist, I believe in the Jewish God, I believe in the
מואבי Moavi god, I believe in all these gods. You know, it's
why I think interestingly, יתרו, Yisro, it also exactly, it's also why
interestingly like you know, יתרו, Yisro, that what do you call it,
that Buddhism, you know, Christianity is sort of seen as more of
a— if somebody decides they're Christian, right, a Jewish Christian, we have
different feelings about like you know, Jews for Jesus or whatever it
might be, you know, than if it's a Jewish Buddhist, right? Well
because you know or maybe I don't know, maybe it's because Buddhism
is more of a philosophy than a religion or whatever, maybe even
a Jewish Hinduist or something, because somehow when you go to another
faith that's exclusive,
right, it's be implicit total complete rejection of this faith, whereas if
you go to another faith that's more syncretist and pluralist and accepts
all different types of things, it's not a complete rejection of your
previous identity. Okay, so anyway, one could imagine forms of, you know,
it's an interesting question, right, about is the worship of or, you
know, is is a rejection of God. Now you could say yes,
that because the very fact that you don't believe that our God
is the ultimate God and they're also on an equal playing field
is a type of a rejection of God. Let's say somebody believed
in, you know, the Jewish God as the one true God, but
believed that there were these other minor deities and worshiped them. You
know, I don't know. So you could speak about a whole range
of when do they, when does different forms of עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara to what degree is it a פורק עול, poreik ol, you
know? We normally don't think in those terms, but it's interesting, if
it wasn't, then you would receive it back, presumably, right, right. So
it's really interesting to think in those sort of theological terms. Okay,
anyway, so because, since it says, so הכרת תכרת. Hikareit Tikareit. הכרת
Hikareit לפני יום הכפורים, lifnei Yom HaKippurim, תכרת Tikareit לאחר יום הכפורים.
le’achar Yom HaKippurim. So even after יום כפור Yom Kippur it doesn't,
יום כפור Yom Kippur doesn't wipe the slate clean. יכול אפילו עשה
תשובה, Yachol afilu asa teshuva, maybe even if you did תשובה, teshuva,
תלמוד לומר talmud lomar עונה בה. avona bah. The sin, you know,
the sin is with the person. לא אמרתי אלא בזמן שעונה בה.
Lo amarti ela b’zman she’avona bah. It's only as long as the
sin, you know, perseveres.
Once you're no longer grasping fast to the sin, then you'll be
forgiven even for these, okay? So you could say that תוספתא Tosefta
how he implicitly learns out that יום כפור Yom Kippur works even
if you haven’t done תשובה teshuva for everything else. These big sins,
you know, יום כפור Yom Kippur doesn’t work unless you’ve done תשובה,
teshuva, right, whereas, so implicitly, everything else יום כפור Yom Kippur does
work even if you haven’t done תשובה. teshuva. Alright, so that's רבי’s
Rebbi position.
יום כפור Yom Kippur could work even without תשובה teshuva except for
these big sins.
Now, okay, ורבנן, VeRabbanan, now how would the רבנן Rabbanan who say
that יום כפור Yom Kippur does not work if you haven’t done
תשובה, teshuva, what would they say? הכרת Hikareit בעולם הזה, ba’olam hazeh,
תכרת Tikareit לעולם הבא. l'olam haba. No, he'd agree with you that
it was talking about these big sins, but the double language of
כרת kareit is not to say after יום כפור. Yom Kippur. We're
not talking in reference to יום כפור. Yom Kippur. We're talking סתם.
stam. Okay, you’ll be cut off in the world to come. Now
if we're talking about the world to come, though, when do you
enter into the world to come? After you die, okay, depending on
how you define world to come or whatever, anyway, after you die.
So what it means is it's not telling you about whether יום
כפור Yom Kippur atones, it's telling you about whether death atones, okay?
So therefore they're saying these big sins death does not atone for
if you haven’t done תשובה, teshuva, same point.
עונה בה, Avona bah, אם עשה תשובה ומת, im asa teshuva u'meit,
it's only as long as you're holding fast to the sin, but
if you've done תשובה teshuva and died, מיתה ממרקת. misa memarekes. Then
sin will cleanse. The phrase of ממרקת memarekes is different than like
מכפרת. mechaperes. ממרקת Memarekes almost is like scours, like it suggests that
it's a little bit more of a difficult process and maybe doesn't
totally clean it the same way מכפרת mechaperes does. But anyway, so
for the רבנן, Rabbanan, what they would say is the
following: יום כפור Yom Kippur only works for people who have done
תשובה. teshuva. Death, okay, works even for people who haven't done תשובה,
teshuva, maybe together with יום כפור, Yom Kippur, רש״י Rashi says. Why
did death sneak in there? Because it's עולם הבא, olam haba, and
עולם הבא olam haba is after you die. Okay, but for the
big three, right, that, you know, only death plus תשובה. teshuva. Michael
wants a chart. I don't have a... Michael wants to know what's
the הלכה halacha of what works. Michael wants to know whether he
really, when does he have to do תשובה? teshuva? That's right.
When does it go until? Like, does it matter here? I want
to know if I have to do תשובה teshuva before יום כפור
Yom Kippur or before I die. Okay? So anyway, so he put
our משנה mishnah as רבי, Rebbi, but you know, could be ודאי
יחיד. vadai yachid. Okay, so basically the way we're reading this thing
is the big three, okay, not the different big three, okay, sort
of this, let's call it the three, okay, פורק עול, poreik ol,
מגלה
פנים, megaleh panim, and מיפר ברית. meifer bris. Okay, so these three,
okay, so by these three, the fact that the פסוק pasuk says
עונה
בה avona bah means that only with
תשובה, teshuva, okay? So I’m trying, I’m figuring out as I’m going.
We've got the רבי Rebbi and the רמב״ם. Rambam. So here’s the
line of תשובה, teshuva, עונה בה. avona bah. Okay, so when you
haven’t done תשובה, teshuva, no atonement, no כפרה, kaparah, after תשובה teshuva
כפרה, kaparah, but, okay, that's what עונה avona says. There’s some that
as long as you’ve done תשובה, teshuva, but in which context? Okay,
הכרת תכרת Hikareit Tikareit is also sort of so with these three,
it's, well, maybe it’d be better to look at it like this,
okay? Okay, these three with תשובה, teshuva, okay, with תשובה, teshuva, you
will because of the עונה בה avona bah you’ll get atonement for,
okay, but what is the before and
after? one way of explaining this line is יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
So you need two things. You need,
you know, even if it's after
יום כיפור Yom Kippur with תשובה, teshuvah, תשובה teshuvah plus יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, okay, I can't do this. I have to think about
how to do this chart. I mean I could just draw it,
I could just make a simple chart. Grid is fine? Fine, you
want a grid. Okay, fine. I can't think about how to do
this. It's okay. Let's move on. Too many factors here. We're moving
on. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so basically that's what you've got. For רבי, Rebbi, יום כיפור
Yom Kippur does, fine, I'll just do it like this. I just
no because I'm trying to I'm trying to sort of incorporate the
the דרשה drasha in the גמרא Gemara and that's confusing me. Okay,
but for רבי, Rebbi, basically here's how we'll do it.
Everything and then the three.
Okay? מיתה mitah or whatever, פריקה, prika, whatever.
Okay. So רבי Rebbi says everything is יום כיפור Yom Kippur without
תשובה. teshuvah. Okay, and these three is יום כיפור Yom Kippur plus
תשובה. teshuvah. That's how רבי Rebbi holds. Whereas the רבנן Rabbanan say
everything else is
מיתה mitah without תשובה teshuvah and this is מיתה mitah with תשובה.
teshuvah. Okay, but once that's what they say about מיתה, mitah, what
do they say about יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? So that's they say
it's יום כיפור Yom Kippur plus תשובה. teshuvah. So you've got two
choices here for the רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay, so what was the initial
question though why do you need יום כיפור Yom Kippur if you
did the תשובה? teshuvah? Oh, that's only by a מצות עשה. mitzvah
aseh. A מצות עשה mitzvah aseh תשובה teshuvah is enough. Oh, okay.
But everything else you also need יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay. So
רבי Rebbi learns the פסוק pasuk is talking about יום כיפור Yom
Kippur and therefore he says יום כיפור Yom Kippur without תשובה teshuvah
works and these things you need יום כיפור Yom Kippur with תשובה.
teshuvah. The rabbis say the פסוק pasuk is talking about מיתה. mitah.
Okay, so מיתה mitah without תשובה teshuvah works for these, but for
the big three you need תשובה. teshuvah. As far as יום כיפור
Yom Kippur is concerned, they say you always need יום כיפור Yom
Kippur plus תשובה. teshuvah. Okay, so that chart was helpful. You did
תשובה teshuvah but you've never really received forgiveness until either יום כיפור
Yom Kippur or you die. Unless it's a מצות עשה, mitzvah aseh,
right, right. Okay, both רבי Rebbi and רבנן, Rabbanan, right? What? Both
רבי Rebbi and רבנן Rabbanan hold that a מצות עשה mitzvah aseh
if you just did תשובה teshuvah you're okay, you're fine. Yep, yep.
Okay. All right,
so now let's go on. Okay, just one minute.
Okay,
רש״י Rashi by the way actually adds in here, דף פ״ה, daf
peh hey, because that's for the רבנן Rabbanan it's מיתה, mitah, רש״י
Rashi adds in here it's מיתה mitah plus יום כיפור Yom Kippur
without if you want it to work without תשובה teshuvah רש״י Rashi
actually says it's with יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But anyway, moving on.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Oh יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. Exactly, then you got some problem. Okay, you better have
done תשובה. teshuvah. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so ומי מצית מוקמת לה כרבי? Umi matzit mokmat lah k'Rebbi?
Now, how can you say our משנה Mishna is going like רבי
Rebbi and it atones for all these stuff even if you haven't
done תשובה? teshuvah? והא מדסיפא רבי יהודה היא רישא נמי רבי יהודה.
Veha mideseifa Rabbi Yehuda hi reisha nami Rabbi Yehuda. The end of
our משנה Mishna is clearly רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so the beginning
must be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda as well. I mean not the
beginning, whatever, we're already towards the end of our משנה. Mishna. דתני
סיפא, Detani seifa, the end of the משנה Mishna says, אחד ישראל
ואחד כהנים ואחד כהן משוח. Echad Yisrael ve'echad kohanim ve'echad kohen mashiach.
So remember the very last point of the משנה Mishna is, is
the atonement for the other sins on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, is
it the same for כהנים kohanim and ישראל? Yisrael? When it comes
to the issue of טומאת מקדש, tumat mikdash, right, the ישראל Yisrael
has the goat on the inside and the כהנים kohanim has the
cow. So when it comes for the all the other sins, do
they all share in the atonement of the goat over the cliff
or are there different, or do the כהנים kohanim get a different
atonement for all the rest of their sins the same way they
have a different atonement for טומאת מקדש? tumat mikdash? That's the question
at the end of the, that's the question at the very end
of the משנה. Mishna. So the first opinion, the anonymous opinion in
the משנה Mishna is that when it comes to all the other
sins, כהנים kohanim and ישראל Yisrael are the same, they're all atoned
for by the goat that goes over the cliff. So the question,
so that גמרא Gemara says that idea that they're all the same
with the goat over the cliff, that's רבי יהודה׳ס Rabbi Yehuda's position.
We'll find out a ברייתא braita that explicitly says that when we
turn the page. So since the end of the משנה Mishna that
says they all share in the atonement of the goat over the
cliff is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the early part of the משנה
Mishna also must be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and not רבי. Rebbi.
We said the early part was רבי Rebbi who says that יום
כיפור Yom Kippur atones even if you haven't done תשובה. teshuvah. Okay,
so let's take a look at that. והא מדסיפא רבי יהודה היא,
Veha mideseifa Rabbi Yehuda hi, since the very end of the משנה
Mishna is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רישא נמי רבי יהודה, reisha nami
Rabbi Yehuda, the beginning is also רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and not
רבי. Rebbi. דתני סיפא, Detani seifa, אחד ישראל ואחד כהנים ואחד כהן
משוח. Echad Yisrael ve'echad kohanim ve'echad kohen mashiach. All those categories, the
כהן, kohen, ישראל, Yisrael, כהן גדול, kohen gadol, they all have the
same atonement. for the other sins. ומאן אית ליה האי סברא? U’man
isley hai sevara? רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. We're going to learn as
we turn, when we turn the page, that it's רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that is the author of that opinion. מכלל דרישא רבי יהודה,
Miklal d’reisha Rabbi Yehuda, so the beginning part where it speaks about
how what the goat atones for is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So
it's not רבי. Rebbe. So אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, רבי
היא וסבר לה כרבי יהודה. Rebbe hi v’savar lah k’Rabbi Yehuda. No,
no, no, it is רבי. Rebbe. רבי Rebbe is the one who
says that יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones, he's the author of the
משנה Mishnah and יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones, the goat of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur atones even if you haven't done תשובה. teshuva. And
he embraces רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position. Yes, it's the same as
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position. He embraces רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position
who says that the כהנים Kohanim and ישראלים Yisraelim get the same
כפרה kaparah with the שעיר לעזאזל. Seir L’azazel. שעיר לעזאזל. Seir L’azazel.
Okay, they have the same atonement. Okay, so this is right, here's
the thing. רבי Rebbe says
יום כיפור Yom Kippur without תשובה teshuva works. Okay, and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says כהן Kohen and ישראל Yisrael are the same with,
you know, the שעיר לעזאזל. Seir L’azazel. שעיר לעזאזל. Seir L’azazel.
Okay, they have the same atonement. Okay, so this is the end
of the משנה. Mishnah. This we said was right before the end
of the משנה, Mishnah, right? Where the משנה Mishnah said that it
works even on an עשה asei and we said it means you
haven't done תשובה. teshuva. So the end of the,
the very end of the משנה Mishnah is a רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda position. The line right before that is a רבי Rebbe position.
So what we're saying is רבי Rebbe is the author of the
משנה Mishnah and he just holds of רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position
when it comes to this. Okay,
so where were we? והא מדסיפא... V’ha midaseifa... Gemara says... מכלל דרישא...
Miklal d’reisha... אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, רבי
היא. Rebbe hi. Yes, the author of the משנה Mishnah is רבי.
Rebbe. וסבר לה כרבי יהודה, V’savar lah k’Rabbi Yehuda, regarding that הלכה.
halacha. אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye. אביי Abaye said, דוקא קאמר
מר? Davka ka’amar mar? Is are you the master, Rav Yosef, who
Abaye is Rebbe? Do you mean to say that precisely this way?
רבי סבר לה כרבי יהודה ורבי יהודה לא סבר לה כרבי? Rebbe
savar lah k’Rabbi Yehuda v’Rabbi Yehuda lo savar lah k’Rebbe? Because there's
two options. You could have said the whole משנה Mishnah is רבי
Rebbe and רבי Rebbe holds of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in this
הלכה. halacha. You could have said the reverse. The whole משנה Mishnah
is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds of
רבי Rebbe in this הלכה, halacha, right? So when you said רבי
Rebbe holds of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, were you saying precisely that
way? רבי סבר לה כרבי יהודה ורבי יהודה לא סבר לה כרבי?
Rebbe savar lah k’Rabbi Yehuda v’Rabbi Yehuda lo savar lah k’Rebbe? But
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't hold of רבי? Rebbe? או
דילמא או מדידרבי סבר לה כרבי יהודה אף רבי יהודה סבר לה
כרבי? O dilma o mididerrebi savar lah k'Rabbi Yehuda af Rabbi Yehuda
savar lah k'Rebbe? So it's all a big lovefest. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda also סבר לה נמי כרבי, savar lah nami k’Rebbe, he also
holds of רבי. Rebbe. They both hold of one another. מיהו, Mihu,
so why did you say רבי Rebbe holds of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and not the other way around? אורחא דמילתא קתני. Orcha d’milsa
katani. למימר דתמיד סבר לה כרבי. L’meimar d’tamid savar lah k’Rebbe. You
wanted to say it in a like in the natural way. The
natural way is רבי Rebbe was the generation after רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. So you said רבי Rebbe embraced the earlier position of רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, which is a more normal thing than to say
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the רבי Rebbe held of a position of
רבי. Rebbe. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the who was the teacher held
of the position of רבי. Rebbe. So אמר ליה אין. Amar lei
in. No, I was being pre-... Yes, I was being precise. דוקא
קאמינא. Davka ka’amina. רבי סבר לה כרבי יהודה ורבי יהודה לא סבר
לה כרבי. Rebbe savar lah k’Rabbi Yehuda v’Rabbi Yehuda lo savar lah
k’Rebbe. רבי Rebbe holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda but רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda did not hold like רבי Rebbe in this position. That
we actually have evidence that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagreed with this
idea that יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones if you haven't done תשובה.
teshuva. דתניא, Detanya, we learn a ברייתא. Baraisa. יכול יהא יום הכיפורים
מכפר על שבים ועל שאינם שבים? Yachol yehei Yom HaKippurim mechaper al
shavim v’al she’einam shavim? Exactly this question. Okay and we're going to
show that this ברייתא Baraisa is a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda ברייתא.
Baraisa. Maybe יום כיפור Yom Kippur would atone whether you've done for
those who have done תשובה teshuva and those who have not done
תשובה? teshuva? ודין הוא, V’din hu, and it makes sense. הוא וחטאת
ואשם שמכפרים ויום הכיפורים מכפר. Ho v’chatas v’asham shemechaperim v’Yom HaKippurim mechaper.
Sin offerings atone and יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones. מה חטאת ואשם
אין מכפרים אלא על שבים. Mah chatas v’asham ein mechaperim ella al
shavim. The same way sin offerings only work for somebody who has
done תשובה teshuva because one part of the bringing of a sin
offering is to do וידוי, viduy, is to do a verbal confession.
אף יום הכיפורים אין מכפר אלא על שבים. Af Yom HaKippurim ein
mechaper ella al shavim. So logically by analogy I should say יום
כיפור Yom Kippur only works on those who have done תשובה. teshuva.
So wait but you could ch-... so that's and that's where we're
going, to say יום כיפור Yom Kippur only works if you've done
תשובה. teshuva. But you could challenge that analogy. מה לחטאת ואשם שאין
מכפרים על המזיד כשוגג. Mah l’chatas v’asham she’ein mechaperim al hamayzid k’shogeg.
One minute, חטאת chatas and אשם, asham, it's not only that you
need to do תשובה teshuva when you bring it, you need to
say a verbal confession. חטאת chatas and אשם asham only work if
the sin initially
was בשוגג, bishogeg, was unintentional, right? There's two points, there's the act
of sin and what's your state now when you're asking for forgiveness.
So a sin offering only works for the sins most deserving in
forgiveness. What are the sins most deserving in forgiveness? When you did
it you were unintentional and now you've done תשובה. teshuva. You get
that? You need both the beginning and the end to be something
that like ameliorates the sin. Initially it was unintentional and now you've
done תשובה. teshuva. So there you understand since they only work for
sins that were unintentional they're not so powerful, the atonement power of
a חטאת chatas and אשם asham is limited and it's only going
to work for somebody who's done תשובה. teshuva. תאמר ליום הכיפורים שמכפר
על המזיד כשוגג? Tomar l’Yom HaKippurim shemechaper al hamayzid k’shogeg? But one
minute, יום כיפור Yom Kippur we know works even for willful sins,
right? That's what it says.
What the
פסוק... pasuk... ומפשעיהם לכל חטאתם. u'mipisheihem l'chol chatosam. Remember we quoted that.
Whether it is willful sins or unintentional sins. So nobody debates that.
יום כפור Yom Kippur works even for intentional sins. So if it
has the power to work for intentional sins, maybe it should work,
maybe it completely wipes the slate, you know, it's a superpower, it's
a super drug or whatever, it's a superpower, powerful תשובה Teshuvah and
atonement, and it works even without תשובה. Teshuvah. הוא למכפר על המזיד
כשוגג, Hu l'michaper al ha'meizid k'shogeg, if it works even for a
willful sin, יכפר שבים ועל שאינם שבים, yechaper shavim v'al she'einam shavim,
maybe it should work even for people who haven't done תשובה? Teshuvah?
תלמוד לומר אך. Talmud lomar ach. אך ביום הזה יכפר. Ach b'yom
hazeh yechaper. What's the פסוק? Pasuk?
Where is it? Where
is the פסוק? Pasuk? 23:27 ויקרא? Vayikra? Yeah. Yeah. אך בעשור לחדש
השביעי הזה יום הכפורים הוא. Ach be'asor lachodesh hashvi'i hazeh Yom HaKippurim
hu. Okay, so אך ach means it's somewhat limited. It does not
have complete scope. Alright? So it only works on those that have,
it only works on
things that you've done תשובה Teshuvah for. Could be that you're a
מזיד, meizid, but only if you've done תשובה. Teshuvah. Okay. Now,
so that's a clear statement that יום כפור Yom Kippur does not
work unless you've done תשובה. Teshuvah. Now, who's the author of that
statement? סתם ספרא מני? Stam Sifra mani? Who is the ספרא? Sifra?
This is a ספרא. Sifra. This is a, the rabbinic exegesis on
the book of ויקרא. Vayikra. That's called the ספרא. Sifra. It's the
collection of מדרש אגדה, midrash agaddah, מדרש הלכה, midrash halachah,
rabbinic legal exegesis, tannaitic legal exegesis on the book of ויקרא. Vayikra.
And we say that the anonymous author, the anonymous voice of the
ספרא, Sifra, we have a tradition is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah. Is
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah. So this exact דרשה drasha which we took
from the ספרא Sifra is a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah position. And
this is saying that it only works on those things that you've
done תשובה Teshuvah for. דקאמר שבים אין לא שבים לא, D'ka'amar shavim
in lo shavim lo, only if you've done תשובה. Teshuvah. Okay. So
now we've got, so within here, right? So we had a רבנן
Rabbanan that we sort of spoke about what they did with the
פסוק pasuk here, but now we have רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah. Okay.
All of this here is everything even במזיד. b'meizid. יום כפור Yom
Kippur works even במזיד. b'meizid. Okay. But רבי Rebbi said only with
תשובה Teshuvah and now we said for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehudah, yes,
it works במזיד b'meizid only if you've done, only, you know, יום
כפור Yom Kippur same thing we said over here. Like יום כפור
Yom Kippur but not dealing with the death. It's the same as
this. יום כפור Yom Kippur only with תשובה. Teshuvah. Yes, it has
the power to work במזיד b'meizid but only with, but only if
you have done תשובה. Teshuvah. Okay, the word אך ach says it
does not work for everything. Okay, so רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehudah, so
if we say the early line in the משנה Mishnah is saying
that יום כפור Yom Kippur works, or the goat of יום כפור
Yom Kippur works even if you haven't done תשובה, Teshuvah, that could
only be רבי. Rebbi. Because here we see that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehudah says that יום כפור Yom Kippur works only with תשובה. Teshuvah.
So the first part of the משנה Mishnah that יום כפור Yom
Kippur works without תשובה Teshuvah is רבי. Rebbi. So רבי, Rebbi, the
author of the משנה Mishnah is רבי, Rebbi, and he holds like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah in this הלכה halachah that it works for
כהנים Kohanim and ישראל Yisrael the same. That's why we said רבי
Rebbi holds like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehudah, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah
does not hold like רבי. Rebbi. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says ורמי סתם ספרא אסתם ספרא. v'rami
stam Sifra a'stam Sifra. I'm going to show you a contradiction of
two anonymous ספראס. Sifras. The one you just quoted says that יום
כפור Yom Kippur only works with תשובה. Teshuvah. Okay.
דתניא, D'tanya, but here's another one: יכול לא יהא יום הכפורים מכפר
אלא אם כן התענה בו וקרא מקרא קדש ולא עשה בו מלאכה.
Yachol lo yehei Yom HaKippurim mechaper ela im kein hisana bo v'kara
mikra kodesh v'lo asa bo melachah. And it's so amazing how radical
the גמרא Gemara is, right? It moves from the goat doing תשובה,
Teshuvah, the goat atoning to יום כפור Yom Kippur atoning. We've had
יום כפור Yom Kippur atoning even without doing תשובה Teshuvah according to
רבי. Rebbi. Now, get ready for this. We're going to have יום
כפור Yom Kippur atone for somebody who violates יום כפור. Yom Kippur.
Here I am. It's on יום כפור. Yom Kippur. I am, I
know יום כפור Yom Kippur atones for somebody that's fasted, וקרא מקרא
קדש, v'kara mikra kodesh, acknowledged the day, like made קידוש Kiddush or
something. Obviously קידוש Kiddush is not necessarily a דאורייתא De'oraisa מצוה, mitzvah,
but it means acknowledged the day. Right? At least you said oh,
today is יום כפור. Yom Kippur. I'm going to go spend a
half hour in שול. shul. Let's say you didn't even acknowledge the
day. You didn't fast, you didn't acknowledge the
day, okay, ועשה בו מלאכה v'asa bo melachah and
you
did מלאכה. melachah. מנין? Minayin? How do you know that even in
that case יום כפור Yom Kippur will atone for you? I love
this. This is so so... תלמוד לומר יום כפורים הוא. Talmud lomar
Yom Kippurim hu. Nope, it is a day of atonement regardless, מכל
מקום. mikol makom. I don't care if you acknowledge or do not
acknowledge it, it starts you over. So that sounds like I mean,
the guy hasn't done תשובה, Teshuva, right? So
and it still works. So how do you reconcile that? So אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, לא קשיא, Lo kashya, הא רבי והא רבי יהודה.
Ha Rabbi veha Rabbi Yehuda. All right, this line of the סיפרא
Sifra is רבי's Rabbi position. You don't need to do תשובה. Teshuva.
And it's taking רבי's Rabbi position one step further. Even if you're
violating יום כפור, Yom Kippur, it atones for you, okay? The earlier
סיפרא Sifra that needed you to do תשובה, Teshuva, that was רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. This is what about the three sins that don't
atone? This isn't one of the three. But in a way, I
mean, why doing all those things aren't you rejecting השם Hashem by
doing all those things on יום כפור? Yom Kippur? No, you're just
rejecting יום כפור. Yom Kippur. Right,
I still believe in God. I believe in God just like, for
whatever reason, I don't care about יום כפור, Yom Kippur, okay. רבא
אמר הא והא רבי. Rava amar ha veha Rabbi. No, they're both
רבי. Rabbi. ומודה רבי בכרית דיומא. Umodeh Rabbi bekareis diyoma. Now this
is interesting because we had just said a minute ago that the
earlier סיפרא Sifra was רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Now that they're both
רבי, Rabbi, so what does it mean that you need to do
תשובה? Teshuva? So now רבא, Rava, it's very interesting, you know, the
Rabbis so wanted to just like, you know, we're so sort of,
you know, wipe the slate clean, the power of יום כפור, Yom
Kippur, that even the earlier סיפרא Sifra that we said was רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that you need to do תשובה, Teshuva, no, that's
רבי, Rabbi, but we're going to explain it in a very narrow
sense. הא והא רבי ומודה רבי בכרית דיומא. Ha veha Rabbi umodeh
Rabbi bekareis diyoma. When it comes to how about
this person that ate on יום כפור? Yom Kippur? Okay, here it
is, it's יום כפור, Yom Kippur, I'm eating. But wait, יום כפור
Yom Kippur atones even for a willful sin even if I didn't
do תשובה. Teshuva. So maybe I don't get punished for eating on
יום כפור Yom Kippur because יום כפור Yom Kippur is atoning for
the sin I'm doing right now of eating on יום כפור. Yom
Kippur. Okay, does יום כפור, Yom Kippur, so do I even get
atonement according to רבי Rabbi for the sin of יום כפור Yom
Kippur itself? So that says, no, no, that's taking it too far,
okay. Maybe if you eat on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, יום כפור
Yom Kippur will atone for your other sins. Violating יום כפור Yom
Kippur doesn't undermine its power to atone for everything else you've done
wrong, but it won't atone for the sin of the violation of
יום כפור Yom Kippur itself. מודה רבי בכרית דיומא. Modeh Rabbi bekareis
diyoma. He agrees by the כרת kareis of the day itself, okay.
דאי
לא תימא הכי, De-i lo tima hachi, because if you don't say
that, כרית דיומא לריבי לית ליה? Kareis diyoma le-Rabbi leis leh?
So the Torah says if you eat on יום כפור Yom Kippur
you get כרת. kareis. But according to רבי, Rabbi, how's that possible?
I'm eating on יום כפור Yom Kippur and יום כפור Yom Kippur
is atoning for me with every bite, okay. It doesn't matter that
I did it במזיד bemezid and didn't do תשובה. Teshuva. So it
must be when it comes to the violation of יום כפור Yom
Kippur itself, maybe יום כפור Yom Kippur still has the power to
atone for everything else, but it's not going to forgive you for
its own violation. So the גמרא Gemara says אלמה לא, Alama lo,
why do you have to say that? I can give you a
scenario where I can say יום כפור Yom Kippur does atone for
violating יום כפור, Yom Kippur, but here's the scenario where you could
get כרת. kareis. משכחת לה כגון דעביד בליליא ומית Mishkhachas lah k’gon
de-avid belayla umis
ולא הוי יממא לכפורי ליה. Velo havi yemama lechapporei leh. Since it
says יום הכפורים Yom Kippurim is מכפר, mechapper, כי ביום הזה יכפר.
Ki bayom hazeh yechapper. Let's say I violated יום כפור Yom Kippur
at night, okay, and then or somebody violated יום כפור Yom Kippur
at night and then died before daybreak. So that person would, that's
the guy the Torah's talking about when the Torah says you get
כרת kareis for eating on יום כפור. Yom Kippur. Because that person
didn't, it needs the day of יום כפור Yom Kippur is מכפר.
mechapper. Okay, so if you ate during the day and dropped dead
a second later, you'd be atoned because the day was atoning for
you as you were eating. But if you ate at night and
didn't live till the next morning to see the day of יום
כפור, Yom Kippur, that's the case that the guy would get כרת.
kareis. So the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute, אלא אימא, Ela
eima,
fine, you'd have that scenario. But כרית דיממא לריבי לית ליה? Kareis
diyemama le-Rabbi leis leh? But the Torah says you get כרת kareis
for eating on the day of יום כפור Yom Kippur because it
says כי כל הנפש אשר לא תענה בעצם היום הזה ונכרתה
מעמיה, Ki kol hanefesh asher lo te'uneh be-otzam hayom hazeh venichrasa me-ameiha,
that if you don't fast
on this day you get כרת. kareis. So according to רבי, Rabbi,
what is the scenario in the Torah if יום כפור Yom Kippur
atones for its own violation, what is the scenario in the Torah
that somebody eats on יום כפור Yom Kippur and gets כרת? kareis?
Because the Torah's describing the person who eats in the day of
יום כפור. Yom Kippur. So how could that be? So as soon
as you're eating you're getting atoned, it must be יום כפור Yom
Kippur does not atone for its own violation. גמרא Gemara says, nope,
I could say יום כפור Yom Kippur atones for its own violation
and I'll give you a scenario somebody eats during the day and
still going to get כרת. kareis. What's the scenario? אלמה לא, Alama
lo, why not? משכחת לה דאכל אומצא וחנקי ומית. Mishkhachas lah de-achal
umtza vechankei umis. Somebody was eating on יום כפור Yom Kippur and
he died as he was swallowing. So that person, you know, the
עבירה aveira has to finish in order to get the atonement. So
since he didn't survive a second after the עבירה, aveira, that person
lost out on the atonement. That's the guy that gets כרת kareis
in the Torah. אי נמי דאכל סמוך לשקיעת החמה, Ei nami de-achal
samukh lishkias hachama, he ate, you know, right up until the last
second of
the
day. ולא הוה ליה שהות לכפורי ליה. Velo hava leh shahos lechapporei
leh.
Anyway, so the גמרא... Gemara... is saying is in theory, if I
really wanted to push it, I could say for according to רבי
Rebbi that יום כיפור Yom Kippur is מכפר mechaper for its own
violation and still say that the case in the תורה Torah where
somebody gets כרת karet for violating יום כיפור Yom Kippur is in
this extremely narrow bizarre case. But רבא Rava is so fine. The
גמרא Gemara I think just wants to demonstrate to you we could
really completely do it ad absurdum in terms of the power of
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But we're going to get close because what
רבא Rava is saying is for רבי, Rebbi, okay, the whole thing
that you know you need תשובה teshuvah whatever, that's only, that statement
that יום כיפור Yom Kippur is only מכפר mechaper with תשובה, teshuvah,
that statement is according to רבי Rebbi and is talking about the
violation of יום כיפור Yom Kippur itself. יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones
for everything even without תשובה, teshuvah, even if you violate יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur,
יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones for all your sins even if you
haven't done תשובה teshuvah for them. The only thing יום כיפור Yom
Kippur does not atone for is the violation of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur itself. Right? If you violated it, it atones for everything else,
but it doesn't atone for the violation of יום כיפור Yom Kippur
itself. That is the one thing you need תשובה teshuvah for, okay?
So now what we're saying here is within יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones without תשובה. teshuvah. We're going to say
except you know even if violated, even if you violated יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, it atones even without תשובה. teshuvah. Okay? But okay, you
know,
יום כיפור Yom Kippur does not
atone for
its own violation without תשובה. teshuvah. That is the one thing that
doesn't work for according to רבי. Rebbi. Okay. Well, that and these
three big ones. Okay. So really maybe it's better to put it
here. For רבי, Rebbi, you know, these three, you know, the thing
you need יום כיפור Yom Kippur and תשובה teshuvah for is these
three plus the violation of יום כיפור Yom Kippur itself. Right? That
you
need, that needs תשובה teshuvah for. But but even if you violate
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it atones for everything even even sins done
במזיד be'meizid and even even a violated יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones
for sins done במזיד be'meizid and if you haven't done תשובה. teshuvah.
Alright. Anyway fine. So that is basically what we have said. So
and therefore our משנה Mishnah is רבי Rebbi and רבי Rebbi just
also holds of רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda's position that the goat works
for כהן Kohen and ישראל Yisrael the same. Okay.
What? What do we hold by?
Yeah, I mean you know how do you פסקן pasken these things,
right? I don't know. But you have I'll tell you how רמב"ם,
Rambam, I mean רמב"ם Rambam rules, right? But the question is what
does it mean to rule?
But I think רמב"ם, Rambam, you know,
I think רמב"ם Rambam rules like רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda because you
know basically we don't want to be, you know, we want people
to be doing the תשובה. teshuvah. I think רמב"ם Rambam says you
know it's only יום כיפור Yom Kippur with תשובה. teshuvah. I mean
I guess there's an important רמב"ם Rambam to read anyway. I'll just
read it to you.
רמב"ם Rambam in תשובה. Teshuvah. Well people might just not do תשובה
teshuvah thinking oh it's in יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Yeah exactly. So
the רמב"ם Rambam starts his הלכות תשובה Hilchos Teshuvah saying the following.
כל מצוות שבתורה בין עשה בין לא תעשה, Kol mitzvot she'ba'Torah bein
asei bein lo ta'asei, excuse me, אם עבר אדם על אחת מהם
בין בזדון בין בשגגה, im avar adam al achat mehem bein be'zadon
bein bi'shigaga, right? Sort of like for you know all the things,
שיעשה תשובה וישוב מחטאו חייב להתוודות. she'ya'aseh teshuvah ve'yashuv me'cheto chayav le'hitvadot.
So you have to do וידוי vidui when you do תשובה. teshuvah.
And then he goes on. Then he says like this.
And he
says,
everybody always needs תשובה teshuvah even if you get מיתת בית דין
misas Beis Din or bring a קרבן, korban, you always need תשובה.
teshuvah. שעיר המשתלח, Se'ir HaMishtaleach, the goat that went over the cliff,
with שהוא כפרה כל ישראל, shehu kapparah kol Yisrael, etc. etc. Okay?
That is מכפר על כל עבירות שבתורה, mechaper al kol aveiros she'ba'Torah,
וכקלות וכחמורות, ve'kakallos ve'hachamuros, the light and the heavy ones, willful, not
willful, our משנה. Mishnah. Right? והוא שעשה תשובה. Ve'hu she'asah teshuvah. So
even the שעיר המשתלח, Se'ir HaMishtaleach, the same way we said יום
כיפור Yom Kippur needs תשובה teshuvah if you're if you don't hold
like רבי, Rebbi, the goat also needs תשובה. teshuvah. Okay? And then
he says בזמן הזה שאין בית המקדש קיים, bizman hazeh she'ein Beis
HaMikdash kayam, אין לנו מזבח כפרה, ein lanu mizbe'ach kapparah, אין שם
אלא תשובה. ein sham ela teshuvah. התשובה מכפרת על כל העבירות. HaTeshuvah
mechaperes al kol ha'aveiros. Okay? And then the question is if תשובה
teshuvah works for everything what what do you need יום כיפור Yom
Kippur for? But anyway רמב"ם Rambam basically rules not surprisingly because רבי
Rebbi is very like reassuring, it's very like very optimistic for people
so you can start over again, but it doesn't create the same
impetus to do תשובה, teshuvah, right? So we're saying our משנה Mishnah's
going like רבי Rebbi and it works for everything even if יום
כיפור Yom Kippur is violated it works for everything without תשובה, teshuvah,
but you know רמב"ם Rambam at least rules, whatever rules means, that
no, that you know it's like רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda that all
this stuff works with תשובה. teshuvah. Let's get a little bit further.
אחד ישראל ואחד כהן ואחד כהן משוח. Echad Yisrael ve'echad Kohen ve'echad
Kohen Mashuach. So again, the goat works equally for these other עבירות
aveiros for ישראל Yisrael or the כהן Kohen or the כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. הא גופא קשיא. Ha gufa kashya. One minute. The language
of the משנה Mishnah just doesn't read smoothly
as the גמרא Gemara's saying. קתני Katani אחד ישראל ואחד כהן ואחד
כהן. echad Yisrael ve'echad Kohen ve'echad Kohen. It says whether ישראל Yisrael
whether
כהן Kohen whether כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and then it says and
what's the difference between them? You just said they're all the same.
So אמר רב יהודה הכי קאמר. Amar Rav Yehuda hachi ka-amar. Here's
what it means. אחד ישראל ואחד כהנים ואחד כהן משוח מתכפרים בשעיר
המשתלח בשאר עבירות. Echad Yisrael ve-echad Kohanim ve-echad Kohen Mashuach miskapprin bi-se'ir
ha-mishtale'ach bi-she'ar aveiros. Whether ישראל Yisrael or כהן Kohen or כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, they all get the same atonement with the goat that
goes over the cliff בשאר עבירות bi-she'ar aveiros with all the other
sins that are not about טומאת מקדש. Tumas Mikdash. ואין חילוק ביניהם,
Ve-ein chilluk beinehem, in the other sins there's no distinction between
them. מה בין ישראל לכהנים ולכהן משוח, Ma bein Yisrael le-Kohanim u-le-Kohen
Mashuach, so where is there a distinction between ישראל Yisrael and כהנים?
Kohanim? אלא, Ella, the distinction only exists when it comes to the
sins of טומאת מקדש. Tumas Mikdash. אלא שהפר מכפר על כהנים על
טומאת מקדש, Ella she-ha-par mekhapper al Kohanim al Tumas Mikdash, when it
comes to the impurity of the sanctuary which there clearly is a
different role between כהנים Kohanim and ישראל, Yisrael, that's where you find
a distinction. Okay? That
the ox atones for the כהנים Kohanim for the impurity of the
sanctuary וקדשיו ve-Kodashav and the goat for ישראל. Yisrael. The reason the
כהנים Kohanim need a separate atonement, you could say two reasons. Number
one is they're more likely to impureify it, they're there the whole
time, and they do the עבודה, avodah, they can do the עבודה
avodah when they're impure. And also they're tasked with preserving and protecting
the purity of the מקדש. Mikdash. So that's where we find a
distinction. Okay. ומני רבי יהודה היא, U-manni Rabbi Yehuda hi, and this
is what we said before, this idea that they're equal when it
comes to the goat for the other עבירות, aveiros, okay, is רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא ותנן ברייתא. De-tanya u-tarnan beraisa. וכיפר את
מקדש הקודש, Ve-khipper es Mikdash ha-Kodesh, okay, he should atone for the
sanctuary. זה לפני ולפנים. Zeh lifnay ve-lifnim. Okay, this is talking about
what the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol does when he brings the goat
and the and the ox inside of the Holy of Holies and
the whole special עבודה avodah of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, so
it atones for the holiness זה לפני ולפנים. Zeh lifnay ve-lifnim. That's
the inner innermost sanctuary. את אהל מועד זה היכל, Es Ohel Mo'ed
zeh Heichal, that's the היכל Heichal which is like where the, you
know, the שולחן Shulchan and the מנורה Menorah were. מזבח ועל המזבח
כמשמעו. Mizbe'ach ve-al ha-mizbe'ach ke-mashma'o. That's the simple sense, okay, which רש"י
Rashi actually says is not is actually the מזבח הזהב Mizbe'ach ha-Zahav
where the incense is brought. Okay, יכפר, yekhapper, he will atone, אלו
עזרות. elu azarot. Those are the like עזרת כהנים, ezrat Kohanim, עזרת
ישראל ezrat Yisrael where the outer מזבח Mizbe'ach is. All of this
is being atoned for by the blood of the ox and the
blood of the goat. Okay. Then it says כהנים ועל הכהנים ועל
כל עם הקהל יכפר Kohanim ve-al ha-Kohanim ve-al kol am ha-kahal yekhapper
is how the פסוק pasuk ends. For the כהנים Kohanim and for
all the people he will atone. כהנים כמשמעו עם הקהל אלו ישראל.
Kohanim ke-mashma'o am ha-kahal elu Yisrael. Okay, כהנים Kohanim and ישראל Yisrael
now again we're talking about the blood of the goat and of
the ox. So here's where they're different. The כהנים Kohanim the blood
of the goat is work- the blood of the ox is working
and ישראל Yisrael the blood of the goat is working. So so
far we said blood of the ox, blood of the goat, one
works for כהנים, Kohanim, one works for ישראל Yisrael atone for all
these places, it cleanses all these places in the מקדש. Mikdash. So
how are they all going to get brought together for the goat?
Because there's one word at the end of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay.
יכפר, yekhapper, it will atone. What does that extra יכפר yekhapper tell
you? אלו הלויים. elu ha-Levi'im. הושוו כולם לכפרה אחת. Hushvu kullam le-khapparah
achas. That extra יכפר yekhapper is saying they're all the same. They
all get a similar atonement. They don't. One has an ox and
one has a goat. So what's the יכפר yekhapper doing? Okay. שמתכפרים
בשעיר המשתלח בשאר עבירות, she-miskapprin bi-se'ir ha-mishtale'ach bi-she'ar aveiros, דברי רבי יהודה.
Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that last יכפר
yekhapper says they're the same. Where are they the same? Not by
the cleansing of the מקדש. Mikdash. They're the same for all the
other sins with the goat that goes over the cliff. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, now רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and this was
the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon quoted in our משנה, Mishnah, כשם שדם
שעיר הנעשה בפנים מכפר ישראל על טומאת מקדש וקדשיו כך דם פר
מכפר על כהנים על טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. keshem she-dam sa'ir ha-na'aseh bifnim
mekhapper Yisrael al Tumas Mikdash ve-Kodashav kakh dam par mekhapper al Kohanim
al Tumas Mikdash ve-Kodashav. So far I agree with you. The blood
of the goat works for טומאת מקדש Tumas Mikdash ישראל, Yisrael, the
blood of the ox works for טומאת מקדש Tumas Mikdash for the
כהנים. Kohanim. But I think when it comes to other עבירות aveiros
they're also split. How are they split? What works for the כהנים
Kohanim for the other עבירות? aveiros? Here's what works. וכשם שוידוי של
שעיר המשתלח מכפר ישראל בשאר עבירות כך וידוי של פר מכפר כהנים
בשאר עבירות. ukheshem she-viddui shel sa'ir ha-mishtale'ach mekhapper Yisrael bi-she'ar aveiros kakh
viddui shel par mekhapper Kohanim bi-she'ar aveiros. Okay, because here's what happens,
right? Here's you've got your goat. We said how we're going to
draw the goat, I don't know, that looks like a little devil
anyway. Okay, here's your goat, okay, right, and this one goes to
the מזבח mizbe- goes to the Holy of Holies, here's the blood.
This one goes over the cliff, ah,
falling down on the cliff. Okay, so the כהן Kohen you remember
when he goes and he does the וידוי, viddui, right, he does
the וידוי, viddui, right, here's the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and he's
putting his hands on it and he's doing the וידוי, viddui, right,
and he says חטאתי, chatasi, right, עויתי, avisi, right?
He's doing that on this one. That's why it takes our sins
and it goes over the cliff. He does not do a וידוי
viddui on this one. Okay, but where but where but when you
get to the big cow, I don't know how to draw a
cow, let's just draw a big thing here. Okay, okay, I don't
know. Anyway, when you get to the big cow, right,
there the כהן Kohen does the וידוי. viddui. He also says, remember
חטאתי, Chatasi, עויתי, Avissi, אני וביתי, Ani u'Beisi, עויתי, Avissi, right? Remember
when we do on the עבודה Avoda of יום כיפור Yom Kippur
on מוסף, Musaf, right? Right? כי ביום
הזה Ki v'yom hazeh whatever, right? We've been doing the וידוי, Viduy,
okay? So here he says, look, he says, here it splits. The
blood of this goat atones for טומאת מקדש, Tumas Mikdash, the וידוי
Viduy of this goat atones for שאר עבירות. Sha'ar Aveiros. Okay? So
he says by the כהנים Kohanim it's also split because you've got
two things. You've got the blood of this cow, okay, the blood
of this cow is טומאת מקדש, Tumas Mikdash, and the וידוי Viduy
of this cow is שאר עבירות. Sha'ar Aveiros. Okay? So what atones
for the,
so he says this goat doesn't atone for the כהנים Kohanim for
the other sins.
This cow atones for the other sins, but there are two parts
of this cow, the blood and the וידוי. Viduy. So the blood
here corresponds to this goat, the וידוי Viduy corresponds to that goat.
Okay? And therefore everything for the כהנים Kohanim is separate from ישראל.
Yisrael. That's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. I find that a
little dispiriting, you know, I'd like to think of us as one
big community when it comes to non-מקדש Mikdash ideas. Okay? I find
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position a lot more attractive. Okay? Let's just
read, I know we're a little over, let's just read one more
sentence. Okay. ולרבי
שמעון U'leRabbi Shimon הא ודאי הושוו, ha vadai hushvu, but wait a
minute, according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon the פסוק pasuk says יכפר,
yechaper, they all have a similar atonement. Where are they getting a
similar atonement? So the גמרא Gemara says no. מאי הושוו? Mai hushvu?
Yes, they're similar in the following way: דבני כפרה נינהו. Debnai kapara
ninhu. They're all going to get atoned for. The end result is
going to be the same, everybody's going to get their atonement. Okay,
מיהו, Mihu, but the process is going to be different. כל חד
וחד מכפר מדינפשיה. Kol chad v'chad mechaper mi'denafshei.
Everybody gets their own separate one even when it comes to שאר
עבירות. Sha'ar Aveiros. For the כהנים Kohanim it is the וידוי Viduy
and for the ישראל Yisrael it is the goat, well the וידוי
Viduy and the goat that goes over the cliff. Okay, מאי טעמא
דרבי שמעון Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Shimon and what's his reasoning? דכתיב Dech'siv
because the verse says ולקח את שני השעירים, V'lakach es shenei haseirim,
take the two goats. אקיש שעיר המשתלח לשעיר הנעשה בפנים. Akish se'ir
hamishtaleach l'se'ir hana'aseh bifnim. It's linked. מה שעיר הנעשה בפנים Mah se'ir
hana'aseh bifnim
the same way the goat on the inside אינו מכפר על כהנים
על טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, eino mechaper al Kohanim al Tumas Mikdash v'Kodashav,
the goat on the inside is only for ישראל, Yisrael, not for
the כהנים Kohanim when it comes to טומאת מקדש Tumas Mikdash and
the goat on the inside it's only for ישראל. Yisrael. דכתיב ביה
אשר לעם, Dech'siv beih asher l'am, the goat that is the people's.
אף שעיר המשתלח אינו מכפר על כהנים בשאר עבירות. Af se'ir hamishtaleach
eino mechaper al Kohanim b'sha'ar aveiros.
So because these two are linked, this is only for ישראל, Yisrael,
this is only for ישראל. Yisrael. You want an atonement for the
כהנים Kohanim for שאר עבירות? Sha'ar Aveiros? You've got to go to
the cow. רבי יהודה אמר לך Rabbi Yehuda amar lach and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say back to you: להכי אקיש. Lehachi akish.
Yes, they're linked in the following way: שהיו שוין במראה ובקומה ובדמים.
Shehayu shavin b'mareh u'v'komah u'v'damim.
They should look the same, they should be bought the same, they
should cost the same, okay? Same height. הוא דאתא. Hu de'asa. Okay.
But they are not the same in that this is only for
ישראל. Yisrael. This is for ישראל, Yisrael, this is
for everybody. Okay? So for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda this is for
everybody and for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon even in שאר עבירות, Sha'ar
Aveiros, you know, they are split off. All right. What's שאר עבירות?
Sha'ar Aveiros? Other sins. All the other sins. So with that second
the goat on the right there, yeah, you said was for ישראל?
Yisrael? This goat for ישראל Yisrael for טומאת מקדש, Tumas Mikdash, for
מקדש. Mikdash. And the cow for the כהנים. Kohanim. This is for
okay everything on the right here that the blood goes there it's
for the sins of the טומאה tumah of the of the מקדש.
Mikdash. Okay, here we can draw it like this. This is מקדש,
Mikdash, right? And this is and this is right all other sins.
All right. So, so, what, so what רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says is right, what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says is this thing of all other sins, that's כהן Kohen
and ישראל. Yisrael. Okay? That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, this
thing of other sins is כהן Kohen plus ישראל. Yisrael. But רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says is no, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you
know what works for the כהנים Kohanim on this side of the
equation? It's the וידוי Viduy here. The right? The חטאתי, Chatasi,
right? The וידוי Viduy here, saying on here, that's what works for
the כהנים Kohanim for the other sins. Okay? The blood works for
the מקדש. Mikdash. But what works, what's gonna work for the other
sins for for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon it is this חטאתי. Chatasi.
Okay?
That's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. It is that וידוי Viduy
that you're doing that works for the כהנים Kohanim for the other
sins. All right, we'll end with that.